Guide to the Lafayette Benedict Mendel Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Lafayette Benedict Mendel papers
1879-1941
MS 1146
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6.75
(17 boxes)
The papers are composed of family and professional correspondence, writings, diaries, scientific notebooks, research files, photographs, and memorabilia which relate to Lafayette Mendel's research on nutrition and growth. Professional correspondents include both Yale colleagues and scientists and nutritionists from around the world. Topical files also document his activities as chairman of the Department of Physiological Chemistry (1920-1935).
Mendel, Lafayette B. (Lafayette Benedict), 1872-1935
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Richard L. and Robert F. Herrmann, 1980, and Benjamin Katzin, 1997.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series and one addition: I. Correspondence, 1905-1941. II. Writings, Notes, and Memorabilia, 1879-1937. III. Topical Files, 1895-1941. IV. Photographs, 1880-1935.
Scope and Contents
Lafayette B. Mendel achieved international prominence as a scientist and educator for his research and teaching in the specialized areas of nutrition and diet. Although the Mendel Papers reflect the career interests of Mendel, they lack any comprehensive research data relative to his scientific investigations. The papers are divided into four series:
I. CORRESPONDENCE
II. WRITINGS, NOTES, AND MEMORABILIA
III. TOPICAL FILES
IV. PHOTOGRAPHS
Series I is divided into select and general correspondence, as originally maintained by Professor Mendel. Select correspondence consists of letters to and from his wife Alice and with nieces and other relatives. (An asterisk next to a name on the folder lists indicates that the folder contains ten or more items.) In addition there are letters of introduction written on behalf of Mendel by Herbert Hoover and F. C. Walcott, as officials of the United States Food Administration. General Correspondence (1905-1940) is arranged chronologically. Mendel corresponded with many of his Yale colleagues as well as with scientists and nutritionists around the world. Individuals of note include: James R. Angell, F. C. Bing, W. B. Cannon, Russell H. Chittenden, Harvey Cushing, R. H. Hubbell, Jacques Loeb, Graham Lusk, Clemens Pirquet, Anson Phelps Stokes, Thomas A. Storey, Victor C. Vaughan, Carl Voegtlin, William H. Welch, and R. S. Woodward. The subjects of this correspondence were often routine matters of lectures, conferences, and congratulatory notes on publications. A smaller portion of this correspondence does focus on the exchange of scientific information and thought relative to Mendel's work in areas of nutrition and growth. This material is incomplete, however, as the research data and enclosures, which are the subject of many of the letters, are missing from the papers. Additional correspondence is also located in Series III, again, as originally maintained by Mendel.
Series II contains the professional writings, student papers, and memorabilia of Mendel. Professional writings include drafts and printed copies of the author's scientific investigations. The subjects of diet, digestion, growth, food economics, nutrition, and Vitamin "A" are some of the areas of research represented. Material here ranges from an early manuscript entitled "Growth" (folders 26-27), to experimental notes and assignments (folders 28-30), to the two-volume edition of Collected Papers (1901-1907), edited by Mendel and Russell H. Chittenden (folders 31-32). Articles published by Mendel are arranged chronologically and have been cited in the various bibliographies (folder 23) compiled and maintained by the author. The articles in the collection are not a total representation of Mendel's work. Files relating to "Physiological Seminary" (folders 40-41) consist of lists of papers reviewed by students and faculty of the Physiological Chemistry Department at Yale. These papers dealt with a variety of nutritional and scientific subjects.
Student writings consist largely of college admission exams, papers, and poetry. Personal journals (1884-1935) and notebooks (1888-1909) also deal primarily, but not exclusively, with the student years of Mendel. Entries in both the journals and cashbooks (1906-1935) are perfunctory personal and financial accounts of activities and expenditures. Entries in the journals often consist of no more than a scribbled "At home" or "Laboratory" to denote the primary locale for the day in question. Notebooks (40 volumes) include class notes from Mendel's undergraduate and graduate subjects, and also contain experimental notes for the later years (1884-1909). The folders of Memorabilia include several eulogies of Mendel, by colleagues, students, and friends, which provide detailed biographical data. Clippings and programs from Yale activities and travel brochures from foreign visits are also present.
Series III contains Topical Files, a distinct set of files created by Mendel on a wide range of topics. These files include correspondence and papers on many specific activities and interests unmentioned or only superficially discussed in Series I. These files contain material on many committees and foundations of which Mendel was a member. Two examples are the American Medical Association's Committee on Foods, and the Commission on Medical Education. Extensive budgetary data and correspondence is present for the Department of Physiological Chemistry, which Mendel was a vital part of from 1892-1935. Additionally, there is correspondence on the Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, relating to grant applications and memberships. Material on the Russell Sage Foundation focuses on the Institute of Pathology, as Mendel served there as director and secretary. Mendel also served as an advisor to the Protein and Nutrition Division of the U.S. Department of Agriculture's Bureau of Chemistry and Soils. Reports and recommendations are included in this file. Other topics of interest focus on the New York Food and Health Exposition of 1932-1933, the Pennsylvania State Emergency Relief Fund, 1933, and "personnel" files which include correspondence to and from Mendel relative to the staffing of academic positions around the world.
Series IV consists of photographs in the Mendel Collection and is a fine complement to the papers. Individual photographs of Mendel in his youth and as an adult, group poses, and individual photographs of the Mendel family, and moments with colleague Thomas Osborne, Mrs. Alice Mendel, Yale students, and while in Germany add a personal flavor to the collection.
The Mendel Papers were donated by Richard L. and Robert F. Herrmann. Additional material was transferred from the Yale Medical Library and the World War I Collection. Related collections holding material by or about Lafayette B. Mendel include the Russell H. Chittenden Papers, and the Sheffield Scientific School Papers. The Herrmann donation was accessioned in 1980.
Biographical / Historical
Lafayette Benedict Mendel was born in Delhi, New York, on February 5, 1872. He received a Ph.D. from Yale University in 1893 and remained at Yale all his professional life, attaining the rank of professor of physiological chemistry in 1903. His research focused on nutrition, particularly the amino acids of proteins and the importance of vitamins in diet. He served on the Inter-Allied Scientific Food Commission during World War I and was a member of the National Academy of Sciences. Mendel died in New Haven, Connecticut, on December 9, 1935.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Medicine; Nutrition -- Physiological aspects; Chemists; Educators; Angell, James Rowland, 1869-1949; Bing, Franklin C. (Franklin Church), 1902-; Cannon, Walter B. (Walter Bradford), 1871-1945; Chittenden, R. H. (Russell Henry), 1856-1943; Cushing, Harvey, 1869-1939; Hubbell, R. H.; Loeb, Jacques, 1859-1924; Lusk, Graham, 1866-1932; McCollum, Elmer Verner, 1879-; Mendel, Lafayette B. (Lafayette Benedict), 1872-1935; Pirquet von Cesanatico, Clemens Peter, Freiherr, 1874-1929; Steenbock, Harry, 1886-1967; Stokes, Anson Phelps, 1874-1958; Storey, Thomas A. (Thomas Andrew), 1875-1943; Vaughan, Victor C. (Victor Clarence), 1851-1929; Voegtlin, Carl, 1879-1960; Welch, William Henry, 1850-1934; Woodward, Robert Simpson, 1849-1924; Yale College (1887- ). Class of 1891; Yale University -- Curricula; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. School of Medicine. Laboratory of Physiology
- Correspondence, 1905-1941; Series I
  - Select
    - Adolph, Edward F., 1917-1923 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Mendel, Mrs. Alice (*), 1920-1936, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Mendel, Lafayette B., 1922-1935, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Selig, Amy, 1924-1926, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Selig, Janet A. (*), 1930-1936, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Selig, Jules (*), 1919-1937, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - United States Food Administration (Herbert Hoover and F. C. Walcott), 1918-1921 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - General
    - 1905-1912 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1915-1929 (Box 1, Folder 9-16)
    - 1930-1941 (Box 2, Folder 17-21)
    - Undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
- WRITINGS, NOTES, AND MEMORABILIA, 1879-1937; Series II
  - Professional
    - Bibliographies, 1894-1935 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - "On the Proteolysis of Crystallized Globulin," Ph.D. thesis (2 drafts), 1893 (Box 2, Folder 24-25)
    - "Growth," pp. 1-71, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - "Growth," pp. 72-151, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Experiment notes, 1898-1918 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Experiment assignments and reference material, 1924-1934 (Box 3, Folder 29-30)
    - Collected Papers, edited by R. H. Chittenden and L. B. Mendel (vol. I), 1901-1904 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Collected Papers, edited by R. H. Chittenden and L. B. Mendel (vol. II), 1904-1907 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Articles, 1896-1904 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Articles, 1917-1930, 1932-1934, undated (Box 4, Folder 34-38)
    - Speech notes, 1917-1918 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Physiological Seminary, list of papers, 1904-1919 (Box 5, Folder 40-41)
  - Student
    - Delaware Academy, Delhi, New York (publications), 1886-1887 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - List of books owned by L. B. Mendel, [ca. 1887] (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Yale College admission exams, 1887, 1893 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Yale College exam booklets, 1887-1892 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Papers and essays, 1890-1893, undated (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Poems, undated (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Journals
    - 1884-1889 (6 vols.) (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - 1890-1892 (3 vols.) (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - 1893-1895 (3 vols.) (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - 1896-1898 (3 vols.) (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - 1899-1904 (6 vols.) (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - 1905-1909 (5 vols.) (Box 7, Folder 53)
    - 1910-1912 (3 vols.) (Box 7, Folder 54)
    - 1913-1917 (5 vols.) (Box 7, Folder 55)
  - Cashbooks
    - 1906-1921 (2 vols.) (Box 7, Folder 56)
    - 1922-1935 (3 vols.) (Box 7, Folder 57)
  - Notebooks
    - 1888-1890 (4 vols.) (Box 8, Folder 58)
    - 1890 (4 vols.) (Box 8, Folder 59)
    - 1890-1891 (4 vols.) (Box 8, Folder 60)
    - 1891 (4 vols.) (Box 8, Folder 61)
    - 1892-1893 (3 vols.) (Box 9, Folder 62)
    - 1894 (2 vols.) (Box 9, Folder 63)
    - 1895-1896 (5 vols.) (Box 9, Folder 64)
    - 1895-1896 (5 vols.) (Box 9, Folder 65)
    - 1897-1900 (2 vols.) (Box 9, Folder 66)
    - 1903 (1 vol.) (Box 10, Folder 67)
    - 1908 (2 vols.) (Box 10, Folder 68)
    - 1908 (1 vol.) (Box 10, Folder 69)
    - 1909 and undated (2 vols. and loose papers) (Box 10, Folder 70)
  - Memorabilia
    - Eulogies, 1925-1937 (Box 11, Folder 71-72)
    - Clippings, 1891, 1926-1936, n.d (Box 11, Folder 73)
    - Yale programs, 1890-1891 (Box 11, Folder 74)
    - Scrapbooks (clippings), 1879 (Box 11, Folder 75)
    - Menus, travel brochures, mailing lists, 1887, 1911-1918, n.d (Box 11, Folder 76)
- TOPICAL FILES, 1895-1941; Series III
  - American Medical Association, Committee on Foods, 1933-1934 (Box 12, Folder 77)
  - American Gastro-Enterological Association Transactions, 1935 (Box 12, Folder 78)
  - Announcements of lectures, 1923, 1930 (Box 12, Folder 79)
  - Associated Grocery Manufacturers of America, award, 1935 (Box 12, Folder 80)
  - Chemical monographs, 1929-1935 (Box 12, Folder 81)
  - Chemical Reviews, 1930-1935 (Box 12, Folder 82)
  - Commission on Medical Education, 1929-1933 (Box 12, Folder 83)
  - Department of Physiological Chemistry
    - Appointments and recommendations, 1921-1929 (Box 12, Folder 84)
    - Budgets, 1921-1925 (Box 12, Folder 85-86)
    - Budgets, 1926-1934 (Box 13, Folder 87)
    - Correspondence, 1920-1936 (Box 13, Folder 88-90)
    - Doctoral recipients, 1895-1935 (Box 13, Folder 91)
    - Graduate School program, 1919-1933 (Box 13, Folder 92)
  - Guggenheim Memorial Foundation
    - Correspondence, 1930-1934 (Box 13, Folder 93-95)
  - Journal of Nutrition, 1932-1935 (Box 14, Folder 96)
  - New York Food and Health Exposition, 1931-1933 (Box 14, Folder 97)
  - Pasteurized milk, 1931 (Box 14, Folder 98)
  - Pennsylvania State Emergency Relief Fund, 1932-1933 (Box 14, Folder 99)
  - Personnel, 1922-1934 (Box 14, Folder 100-101)
  - Pharmacology, 1933-1934 (Box 14, Folder 102)
  - Resignations, 1935-1936 (Box 14, Folder 103)
  - Rose, Mary Swartz (eulogy), 1941 (Box 14, Folder 104)
  - Russell Sage Institute, 1926-1935 (Box 14, Folder 105)
  - U.S. Department of Agriculture, Bureau of Chemistry and Soils, 1930-1935 (Box 14, Folder 106)
  - Writings (by other scientists), 1887-1931 (Box 14, Folder 107)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, [ca. 1880-1935]; Series IV
  - Mendel, L. B. (youth), [ca. 1880-1891] (Box 15, Folder 108)
  - Mendel, L. B. (adult), [ca. 1892-1935] (Box 15, Folder 109)
  - Mendel, L. B. (in groups), 1900-1918 (Box 15, Folder 110)
  - Mendel, L. B. (with wife, Alice), 1925-1933 (Box 15, Folder 111)
  - Mendel, L. B. (with students and faculty), 1899-1904 (Box 15, Folder 112)
  - Mendel family (groups), 1885-1992 (Box 15, Folder 113)
  - Mendel family (individuals), 1892-1905 (Box 15, Folder 114)
  - Breslau, Germany (groups and buildings), 1895-1896 (Box 15, Folder 115)
  - Delhi, New York (groups and buildings, including family business,), undated (Box 15, Folder 116)
  - Yale--student rooms, 1890 (Box 15, Folder 117)
  - Yale and University of Virginia medical buildings (interiors and exteriors), 1901, 1926 (Box 15, Folder 118)
  - Men, 1896-1907, undated (Box 15, Folder 119)
  - Children, 1895-1917, undated (Box 16, Folder 120)
  - Allantain photos [snowflakes?], undated (Box 16, Folder 121)
  - Laboratory specimens and animals, undated (Box 16, Folder 122)
- Additional Material, 1917-1934, undated; Accession 1998-M-099
  Scope and Contents
  This addition is composed of correspondence and writings from the office of Lafayette B. Mendel in the Department of Physiological Chemistry. The chairman of the department, Dr. C. N. H. Long, ordered the disposal of Mendel's files. Dr. Benjamin Katzin, then a graduate student, was allowed to look through the files and saved these few folders of material as a representative sample.
  Correspondence comprises the bulk of this addition. It is arranged in chronological order. Letters of Elmer Verner McCollum and Harry Steenbock, fellow scientists interested in nutrition, are included.
  - Correspondence, 1917-1934 (Box 1, Folder 1-7)
  - Writings, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Fragments and unidentified, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)